[Music]
hey guys welcome to my 2021 react crash
course
so it's been about two years or so since
my last one and i wanted to create an
updated version and this course is meant
for beginners i'll be explaining some of
the core concepts and fundamentals of
react
we're going to be building a task
tracker application
looking at components props state we're
going to
use react hooks and we're also going to
be
dealing with something called json
server which is a mock rest api or
kind of like a fake back end that we can
use so i can show you how we would use
react in a full stack application
where we're making requests to an api
we're going to look at routing
and a whole bunch of other stuff so the
first thing i want to do is just go
through some slides and then we'll go
ahead and jump into
writing code so first off what is react
the standard definition is it's a
javascript library for building user
interfaces
and you may have heard of it referred to
as a framework i refer to it as a
framework most people do and i'll talk
about
why in a second now react is uh it was
created and it's maintained by facebook
it's strictly front end meaning it runs
in the browser when you have a web app
that's built with let's say php
you're you're running php on the server
your app is hosted on the server and
then
it serves html templates or html pages
to the client
with react you build what's called a
single page application
or a spa where you have a single html
page and then all of your routing
all that stuff is done through react
which then compiles to a javascript
bundle that's loaded by the browser
so it makes for really fast and
interactive interfaces
now even though react is a front-end
framework so if you can't directly
for instance communicate with your
database
it's often used in combination with
other technologies to create a full
stack application
for instance the mern stack which is
really popular it's mongodb which is a
type of database
express which is a back-end framework
react and then node.js which is a
javascript runtime
you could also use react on the front
end and use php laravel on the back end
or python django
and what you would do is you would you
would serve json data from your server
and you would make requests from react
to the server
to get data to to add data update delete
and so on
now as far as being a library versus a
framework
most people call it a framework and
that's because it's directly comparable
to
something like angular or vue.js now it
doesn't
have as much included as angular does
like angular has a built-in routing
system
react doesn't you just have to install
an extra package called react router dom
so it has an entire ecosystem of
packages that you can install to make it
function as a full-fledged framework
now as far as a library goes when i
think of a library i think of like
jquery
low dash something where you you pull
utilities in and you use them in your
application
react doesn't work like that it works
more like like
angular or view and those three are
actually the top frameworks in the
industry right now
uh i would go as far as to say react is
the most popular
but the other two are great as well i
have crash courses on those
i'll be updating soon so when you're
choosing one of these three frameworks
if you're you know if you're going to be
a front-end developer or full stack
developer
you just want to compare them use each
one test them out see what
what you really click with and also look
at jobs in your area if that's what if
that's what your goal is
all right so we know that react is a
front end library slash framework
now why would you want to use it there's
actually a bunch of reasons but one of
the biggest
is it gives you a way to structure the
view layer of your application
so mvc or model view controller is a
popular design pattern for software
the model deals with the data the
controller deals with the requests and
routing
and then the view is the ui the user
interface the part of the app that the
user sees
react is basically the v in mvc
now if you've tried to build a large
dynamic interface using javascript
vanilla javascript it can get really
messy your html
your styling and your javascript logic
are just all over the place
and everyone writes vanilla javascript
differently
react allows you to build your ui using
what are called reusable components
so every part of your user interface is
looked at as a dynamic component
that can hold its own state and data
we also don't have to separate our
markup from our logic because react uses
something called jsx or javascript
syntax extension
and this allows us to to basically write
dynamic html
it's actually javascript but it's
formatted like html
we can even embed javascript expressions
variables etc now
the apps that you build with react are
very interactive because it uses
something called the virtual dom
which is the document object model so it
what this does it allows you to update
parts of the page that need to be
updated
without reloading it so if you have a
list of users or in our case a list of
tasks
and you want to delete one of them it
doesn't have to reload the page it does
everything behind the scenes
if you were to build let's say a
traditional php application where you're
just serving
html templates every delete you make it
most likely is going to have to refresh
the page
so this makes things much more faster
more dynamic and interactive
react also has performance and testing
benefits
another huge reason to learn react is
it's it's very big in the industry right
now
just by the way it structures everything
it makes it much easier to work on
projects with teams
rather than just having you know a bunch
of jumbled javascript
so managing data is also really easy
with one-way data binding
all the data in your state is immutable
meaning you can't mutate it directly
and react provides ways to to basically
recreate your state every time that it
needs to be changed
so this this helps with debugging and
also offers better
performance so what should you know
before learning react
this this can vary depending on on
person to person but
generally you want to have a good handle
on javascript you don't want to go from
learning html and css and then jump
right into react
you should know all the fundamentals of
javascript including things like data
types variables
functions loops etc in react and
javascript in general you work with a
lot of asynchronous code
so you should be familiar with things
like promises array methods such as
for each map filter reduce these are all
commonly used in react applications
so get familiar with those doing
algorithms
that's a really good way to practice
these array methods
and then the fetch api is used to make
http requests
to either your own back-end server or to
a third-party api
for example the github or youtube api so
get familiar with fetch
again i have crash courses on most of
the stuff that you can check out if you
want
so as i said with react in pretty much
any front-end framework you're going to
be looking at your user interface as a
bunch of components
so here's the app we'll be building it's
called just called task tracker it's
pretty simple you just add a task
with a day and a time you can set a
reminder and you'll be able to double
click and
and set the reminder to either true or
false which will show this border
and we can delete and so on now over
here i just have outlined or created a
border around
each of the components so we have the
green around the header component
and inside the header we have a button
component we have the
add task component here which we could
actually break down even further and
create
input components as well if we wanted to
down here we have the tasks
component the purple which wraps around
all of these and then
each individual task is also its own
component
all right then we have down here the
footer component we're also going to
look at routing a little bit so we'll
have we have this about link
and that's going to go to a separate
route that will show the about component
all right so you can go to any website
or any ui
you go to twitter and and look at the
different components the list of tweets
each tweet itself the the box to post a
tweet
your all your followers everything can
be looked at as a component
so that's kind of the mind frame that
you want to be in when you're working
with react
or even angular view now as far as how
we create components in react
they can be created with both classes
and functions or functions i should say
now we'll be focusing mostly on function
components with hooks which seems to be
kind of
the more common way to do things these
days in my 2019
react crash course we focused on classes
so
if you really want to dive into into
class-based components you can check
that the older crash course out so on
the left we have a component called
header this is formatted as an arrow
function but
of course it could be a traditional
function as well it simply returns a div
with an
h1 now on the right is the same
component as a class
and you can see it's defined as a class
and it extends react.com
which is going to give us everything in
the in the the root component class to
work with
including the render method which takes
care of rendering it out on the screen
and in render we're just returning the
same thing we're returning here
now what's being returned looks like
html but it's actually just syntactic
sugar
for javascript which is called
javascript syntax extension or jsx
and it's similar to the html syntax
aside from a few things like instead of
the class attribute you have to use
class
name but in addition to that you can
also put any kind of javascript
expression
into your jsx to make it dynamic and
then once you have your component
created you can embed it into other
components with this type of syntax
which is similar to like xml
so we would just have header we can also
pass in props which are
basically attributes so we could pass in
a title of whatever we want
into the component and then work with it
inside of the
either the function or the class
whatever we're using
all right so components are not just
static markup they're dynamic and they
can
contain something called state so state
is basically just an object that
determines how a component renders and
behave
so an example would be if you have let's
say a collapsible menu
that would have an open and closed state
so you might have a state
object in your component that has a
value of open that could be either true
or false
now if you have a list of users or
tasks or whatever it might be that's
also part of the state so any data that
you bring into your components that's
going to be part of the state and a lot
of times you want to share that data
across
multiple components so in that case you
would use what's called
either app state or global state now
sometimes you end up having just a ton
of app level state that gets really
difficult to manage
so in that case you have a few options
you could use the context api which is
built into react
or you could use a third-party state
manager like redux
which is way beyond the scope of this
crash course but i did want to mention
it and i do have other videos on those
now prior to react version 16.8 we had
to use class components
if we wanted if we wanted to hold state
so
function components were actually called
dumb components because
they couldn't hold state however in
version 16.8
react introduced something called hooks
which allow us to
use state and other lifecycle functions
within function components
and that's what we'll be focusing on in
this crash course
specifically the use state hook which
allows us to return a stateful value
along with a function to update it
there's other hooks as well
use effect is used to perform side
effects in function components
we'll be using that towards the end um
one of the biggest uses for
use effect is to make http requests when
the page loads
so if you're fetching data from an api
on page load you'll want to use use
effect
there's a bunch of others as well
there's use context user reducer
but those are beyond the scope of this
crash course all right so if those last
few slides didn't really make much sense
at all don't worry about it because
we're going to
do we're going to have plenty of
examples throughout the course and
throughout this
application that we're going to build so
we're going to build out our user
interface first and then also implement
towards the end something called json
server
which we're going to use is kind of a
fake back end so you can see
how react would work if you were
building a full stack application and
making requests to a back end or an api
all right so enough with the slides
let's go ahead and jump in and let's get
started with react
all right so we're going to get started
now there's a bunch of ways to
basically start a react application one
of the most common
and easiest ways is using a program
called create react app which is a cli
it's a command line interface tool
to just easily get up and running and
set up a boilerplate with all the files
and folders and packages that you need
it also has a development server it has
a way to build out your static assets to
deploy
so to install this we need to use npm
which is the node package manager
and in order to use that you have to
have node.js installed on your system
i'm sure that a lot of you already do if
you don't just go to nodejs.org
download it install it doesn't matter if
you're on you know windows
mac or linux another thing i would
suggest installing is the react dev
tools if you're on chrome there's a
chrome extension there's a
firefox extension as well and it just
allows you to kind of see all the
components and props and state
of your react application so we're going
to install this
we're actually going to use the npx
command instead of installing it
globally with npm
what this does is it just runs create
react app and
creates the the folder for us rather
than installing create react app
on your system so first of all make sure
you have npm
you can do npm-version make sure it's
above 5.2 where you won't be able to use
npx
and then let's do npx create dash
react app and i'm going to call this
task dash actually let's call it
react dash task dash
tracker because i will be doing a vue.js
in angular course and we'll be doing the
same
application and this is just going to
set up
all of the files and folders that we
need it's going to install all the
packages that we need and so on
okay so that's all set now you just want
to open that folder up in your text
editor i'm using vs code so i'm going to
cd
into what i call it react dash
task tracker and i'm going to run code
and then
dot which just means i want to open vs
code in the current folder
all right so now over here you can see
all the files and folders i'm just going
to make this bigger for now
and i just want to go over some of this
so package.json
if we look at the dependencies that are
included of course we have the react
library
we have react dom which is responsible
for rendering our react application out
to the document object model
to the browser if you were to use let's
say react native
you'd have the same react library but
you would also have react native instead
of react dom
okay react scripts comes with you know
the development server the build tool
and so on everything that create react
app offers
and then you have some testing libraries
which we're not going to get into in
this crash course
down here we have our start script so
npm start will run the development
server on local host 3000
npm run build will build out our static
assets for deployment
and we have tests for testing and then
eject
will basically allow you to if you want
to like change something in the webpack
config if you want to expose
other libraries and packages that are
kind of hidden
that run behind the scenes you can eject
but there's there's really not a lot of
cases in where you would
have to do that all right so let's go
ahead and run the dev server i could run
it just in my terminal here but i'm
going to go ahead and command tilde and
open up my integrated terminal
envious code so from here we can run npm
start and that's going to start up the
dev server
so this when this starts up on localhost
3000 this is the development build if
you look at the react dev tools if you
installed them it says this page is
using the development
build of react if you deploy i'm sorry
if you
build you'll have all your static assets
in the build folder if you run it from
there it'll say it's the production
build
all right so let's close this stuff up
we don't need that
and i'm just going to we'll make this
smaller so we can see both of these at
the same time
and i just want to go over some of the
other stuff we have here so in the
public folder we have an index.html
so this is essentially the the single
page of the single page
application that's being loaded and it's
actually really simple there's a bunch
of comments here
that make it look more complicated than
it actually is
so we'll just get rid of these but it's
just a simple html file
and we have some meta tags and some
stuff in the head but
if you look in the body all there really
is is a div with the id of root
so this is kind of the gateway to our ui
to our react application
and the way this works if we look in the
source folder which is where we put all
of our components and state and
everything
that has to do with our app that we're
building
if we look in the index.js here which is
kind of the entry point for react
we're importing react or importing react
dom and then
there's a method on reactdom called
render
and what we're doing is we're grabbing
that div that i just showed you with the
id of root
with document.getelementbyd root
and we're inserting our app into that
div
now this app comes from app.js which
we're importing right here
and app.js contains the root app
component
so remember i said to think of
everything in components well
app is the root app i'm sorry the root
component
so every component that we create like
our header our events
footer the ad form although all that
stuff is going to be
in this main root app component okay and
then that is what's being put
into that div right here okay
so i just wanted to kind of explain that
now uh
let's actually just want to change the
title here we'll
change it to task tracker
and you could put like a if you want to
use the bootstrap cdn or something like
that you could use this file for that
kind of thing
but we'll go ahead and save that and
this updates right away
or it should i don't know why it didn't
that time
but this will auto reload so i want to
go into
now app.js and this is the root app
component and everything that you see
here
is coming from this component here
so we're importing logo which is uh this
logo svg it's this
spinning react logo we're also importing
an app css file which is just some basic
styling
and then we have a function now remember
components can be
functions or classes most people
these days seem to use functions with
hooks which is what we'll be focusing on
but this could
this could be a class i might give you
an example of that
but if we look in the return of this
function it looks like
html but this is actually jsx javascript
syntax extension
and there's a few differences for
instance you might notice class name
we can't use the class attribute to
assign a class we use classname
same with four if you have a label with
a four attribute you don't want to use
four in react you would use
html4 like that all right so just keep
that in mind
um you cannot this is also dynamic we
can have javascript expressions and
variables
here we're bringing in logo adding it to
the source of the image
what i'm going to do though is just get
rid of everything that's inside of this
div
and for now let's just put if you want
emmett to work in here you can see it's
not working right now
it might for you if it doesn't click
where it says javascript
you can change that to javascript react
and then it should work so let's just
say hello
from react for now i'm going to save
that
and this will auto reload and we don't
need to
bring in the logo and app css
and we also don't need some of these
files anymore so logo i'm going to get
rid of app css
i also don't want app test and setup
test since we're not dealing with that
so we'll go ahead and delete those four
files just to clean things up a little
bit
now when we're returning this this jsx
here
you can only return a single parent
element so you can put whatever you want
in this div and it doesn't have to be a
div
it can be a paragraph it could be a
heading it could be just a fragment
which i'll show you in a second
but if i go under here and i try to put
like let's say an h2
and i say hello you'll see i'm already
getting an error here and it won't
compile
so it says jsx expressions must have one
parent element
so whatever you return it has to be a
single element and then anything else
any other
other components or whatever you want
can go inside of it so i'm going to move
this h2
up into the div and that should fix it
okay
now let's go ahead and open up the
dev tools here i'm going to go to the
elements tab just to show you what
what this compiles to so we have a div
with the id of root that wraps around
our entire ui
and we have this div with the class of
app and then our headings so we're
seeing
this right here now obviously class name
is going to compile out to just a
regular html class
if you don't want to have a div or any
element around like these
these headings or whatever we have in
here we could just use
a fragment or just an empty angle
bracket
if i save that and we check it check
this out it's just the h1 and h2
of course we still have the root div
which wraps around everything but
as far as this component goes it's not
going to have a div or anything wrapped
around these
but i actually do want a div and i'm
going to have a class name of container
for some styling that i'm going to add
later okay so you'll see that that gets
changed to
div with the class of container now we
can add
expressions in here we can use variables
so for instance if i were to
say const name and make sure you do this
above the return of course
and set a name to brad and i go down
here and i put in some curly braces i
can then put
name in here and i get hello brad okay
i can also do like we could say one plus
one and that's going to
render out to two i can do
conditionals as ternary operators so
let's say
const x equals true and then i could go
down here and i could say
if x then we'll show
yes else then we'll show no
and this is just a ternary operator so
hello yes if i change this to false
and save we get hello no all right so
you can write javascript directly in
here
which makes it really nice really it
really
dynamic all right so i'm just going to
get rid of that
and now we're going to work on just
creating our own components
okay remember i said to think of your
your app or your user interface as just
a bunch of components
so we're going to start with the header
i'm going to go over to source
my source folder create a folder called
components
and this is where we're going to create
all of our components the first one
we're going to call let's see we're
going to call this
header.js uppercase oops didn't mean to
do that
uppercase h that's just the convention
for components
and this could be a class or a function
and there's an extension for vs code
that i'd highly recommend if you're
using it if you're using vs code and
that's es7 react redux graphql react
native snippets
which has a bunch of snippets for things
like imports exports
even like loops and just regular
javascript stuff
but it also has these these snippets for
components
so rcc will create a class based
component
rce will create a class component but it
will export
down at the bottom here the one that i
like to use is the arrow function
it's i believe it's rafce
this one right here so it's nice and and
and clean it's just an arrow function
that exports down at the bottom
so what i'll do is just do our a with
that extension installed
r a f c e enter and that creates just a
boiler plate of a component
of an arrow function component now this
here
it's importing react because this used
to be required
for every react component however we
don't need this anymore so we can
actually get rid of it
now as far as what i want to output for
the header i'm going to use a header tag
as my just parent element
and then we'll put an h1 in here and
we'll say
task tracker
now if i save it nothing's going to
happen we because we just created the
component we didn't put it into
our application so back in our app.js
let's go ahead and import header
from and we want to go into dot slash
components
slash header and we just embed it just
like it was uh like an xml tag
so header just like that
save it and now we have task tracker
now just to show you a class based
component real quick i'm just going to
comment this out and if we use a class
we do need to import
react from react
i haven't i haven't done a class in
quite a while
so we could say class we'd call it same
thing app but we need to extends
react dot component because we need all
the
life cycle methods and all that and then
we'd have a render
so render takes care of the output
and then in this render we would return
whatever we
want as far as jsx i'll just put in h1
and say hello
from a class now if i save that i
believe we're gonna have to reload since
we
yeah so now we get hello from a class
and just make sure we have no errors
here
header is defined but never used that's
fine all right so i mean if you want to
use classes you can
and you can check out my older crash
course if you want to
just use classes but i'm going to go
ahead and delete that
and that and let's
uncomment this and there we go so now we
have our header back
now i want to talk a little bit about
props because you can pass
stuff in here like if we want to pass in
a title to our header and
for now we'll just say hello now it's
not going to do anything because we're
not handling it but we can pass
anything we want in to retrieve this
prop inside of our component here
we take in props as as a parameter
and then down here let's say we want to
replace this
static text with our props dot
title if i save that now we see hello
because that's what's being passed in
now we can also have default props so if
i don't pass anything in here
and i save that that's not going to show
anything because there's no title
however i could go below the the
function
the component say header dot default
props and set that to an object and set
the title
to task tracker
now if i save that that's going to show
up because that's the default if i were
to again
pass something in here it would
overwrite the default
now this props dot title we could we
could clean this up a little bit
props is going to it's just going to be
an object of whatever props you pass in
so we can destructure
so we can just add curly braces and take
in the
title and then down here we don't need
to do props dot title we can just go
like that and that's going to give us
the same exact result now there's also
prop
types which is kind of like a built-in
type system for your properties
it's not like it's not something you
have to use but it's something that
will will help you out and make your
code a little bit more robust
i'm not going to focus on creating prop
types for
everything but i just want to kind of
show you how it works
now with the extension the es7 react
extension you can do
impt to import prop types
and then what we can do is go down here
and say header
dot prop types lower case
set that to an object and we know we
have a title so
the title and we can create a type do we
want this to be a string a number a
boolean
we want this to be a string so uppercase
p prop types
dot string now if i were to
go back here and pass in let's say title
and pass in a number now if you're
passing in a number or a boolean or
something
you want to have it wrapped in curly
braces but we'll pass in a 1
and right away down here in the console
it's still going to render but you'll
see we get this warning
invalid prop title of type number
supplied to header
which expects a string okay so it's just
a way to kind of make your code more
robust and catch
errors before they happen and you can
also use something like typescript with
react as well
all right and then if it's required you
can do dot is
required as well
all right and we have a default prop so
it's not going to give us any error but
if i were to get rid of the default prop
and reload you'll see i'll get a warning
down here
all right so we'll go ahead and keep
keep header as is
and i want to talk a little bit about
styling because there's a few ways you
can do
you know css within react so one is to
just use
a style sheet which is what ultimately
we're going to do i'm going to use this
index css i already have some styles
prepared
but you can also use something like
style components which is an external
package that is really popular you can
also use
direct css in javascript
so i'm going to give you an example of
that so this h1 here
we could set style and when you use
style you want to use double
curly braces if you're doing it in line
like this and let's say we wanted to
change
let's say color and we would set that to
a string
of you know whatever color value so if i
set that to red
if i want to add something else i'd put
a comma like say background color
now it's not going to be background dash
color like
css it's going to be camel case like
this
and set it to a string so we'll say
black save that
okay another thing we can do if you
don't want to do it in line like this
you could create a variable down here we
could say
our heading we'll say heading style
and set that and then just grab
both of these cut that out
put those in here and then use single
curl
single curly braces here and pass in our
heading style and that's going to do the
same thing
all right i'm not going to be using this
except where
we have some dynamic styling so i'm
going to get rid of this
but i will keep this down here just to
kind of remind you that you can
do this we'll say css
in js all right now i'm going to add
some css so this index style sheet we're
going to get rid of that
and you can get this code you can get
this whole
this whole thing in the github
repository in the description so just
grab the styling
paste it in i'll go through it real
quick it's pretty simple we're using the
poppins font
we have a reset the container is going
to be 500 pixels wide with a border
header is going to be flexbox we're
going to have a button on the side
button classes button styles
events so our list of events will be
styled our form
and form control and then our footer so
pretty simple i'm going to go ahead and
save that
and it's going to look like this let me
just make this a little wider
like that all right
so we'll close that up and we shouldn't
have to touch the index css anymore
now the next thing that i'd like to do
here is
um add a button so
next to the h1 let's put a button here
and this is going to say add for now
so we save that yeah we
also want to add a class here of header
because that's what i have in the style
sheet
that's going to make it a flexbox and
align it
side by side and then i also oops that
should be class name
and then i also want to add a class
name here of btn i'm using single quotes
all right so now we have our button
so as far as
components go you can make whatever you
want into a component
so if we want this if we want to create
a button
button component in case we want to add
more buttons with maybe different colors
and different texts and events
we can do that so i'm going to create a
file in components called button.js
and we're going to just map out a
function here
and we don't need this
so i'm actually going to copy or not
copy but cut
this out of here and we're just going to
return
this button directly and then
in our header we're going to bring that
button component in
so it's in the same folder so just dot
slash button and then we'll put that
here
and we're going to see the same result
now i want to be able to take in a
couple props
into this button so one will be color
so we'll pass in a color of let's say
green
we'll have text let's say
add actually let's change it just so we
can make sure that we're actually seeing
that
so we're passing in a green and text
prop
into buttons so remember we catch props
here we could just use props
and use it as an object but i'm going to
destructure that object
and take color and text
and let's add right here instead of the
static
add text we'll add our prop and then for
the color
we'll go ahead and add style and set
that
to let's use double
curly braces here and we're going to
actually set the background color
so background color is going to be set
to color
so we'll save that and now we have a
green button that says hello
so if we wanted to add other buttons you
know we could
copy this down and this one here oops
this one here we could say
hello one this one hello three and we
could
change colors blue
red so this is what what i mean by
reusable components obviously that
doesn't look good but
you get the point we can have we can
reuse this component with different
props
so i just want the first one and i'm
going to change the text to
add and save that
and then in our button we can also have
you know default props so we could say
button dot
default props and we could set the
color let's set that to we'll use
i don't know steel blue
and we could also use our prop types
so up here import our prop types
and button dot
this actually won't this first one is
going to be lower case this confused me
for a long time
so we have our text which is going to be
prop types dot string
and then we have the color
now we're going to be we're going to get
into
events you know quite a bit throughout
this course but let's just
let's talk a little bit about that now
so let's say i want to have an event on
this button
i could just add right here i could say
on
click and set that to a function
called on click and i could go up here
and create that function so
const on click
and we could do a console log and just
say
click so if i go over here if i click
you can see it's going to log that down
here you can also pass in the event
object so if you want to get you know
the position of the the element that's
clicked or whatever there's there's a
lot of things you can access with that
um but since this is a component where
it's not always going to have the same
click
so what we'll do is we'll have that
click as a
prop right so in here let's say on
click and for now we'll just set this to
a function here called on click in our
header
so const on click this isn't going to
stay i'm just
putting it here for now and we'll say
console log
click all right now this is getting
passed in as a prop so in our button
we have to catch it here just like we
did with the other ones
and we can get rid of this because
what's going to happen is this will call
this on click and it will get sent up to
the header
or wherever you embed this button now
down here in the prop types we could add
on click say we want that as a prop
types dot funk because it's a function
and we could say it's it is required
because
you're most likely going to want a
button to click
uh well actually no we'll get rid of we
don't need that and it's required
so we'll save that now if i go and
let's just reload that and click add we
see click
okay because we embedded this button
component and we
had the on click prop just call this
function here
now we're going to later on this is
going to toggle the the form but we're
not going to do that just yet
i just kind of wanted to give you an
idea of how events work
i could also i could have made it a
double on double click on submit there's
a whole bunch of different events that
you can add
now i want to start to talk about state
and
we're going to start dealing with our
tasks so let's close up header and
button
and we're going to create in components
i'm going to create a new file
called tasks.js so this is our task
component so let's sketch out a
component here
and we can get rid of this and for now
i'm just going to create a variable
called tasks up here and set that to an
array
and i'm just going to paste in three
different tasks they're just
objects with an id text day and a
reminder which is just a boolean value
all right now ultimately this is not the
way that we want to do this we want the
task to be part of our state
so i'll show you how to integrate that
into our component in a minute but i
just want to first show you how we can
map through these or loop through these
tasks and output something based on you
know for each one
so we do that by creating what's called
a list and we create a list by using the
map array method which is just
javascript
you should be familiar with like for
each map
filter and so on i'm not going to really
explain those too much
but in this tasks let's uh
we actually don't need a div so we'll
just use a empty fragment here
and then i'm going to open some curly
braces and take
my tasks and
we want to do dot map to create a list
now map takes in a function so i'm going
to use an arrow function
and i'm going to set this just to some
parentheses with some jsx inside
now for each task i'll call it task
and then in here let's just for now
we'll put an h1
let's do like an h3 and let's say
we want the task dot is it text
yeah so we'll just get the text for each
one and i'll put that
all right if i save that nothing shows
because we haven't brought in the task
component yet so let's go up here into
app.js
and let's say tasks
tasks and then go under the header here
and say
tasks all right so we'll save that
and notice that it's showing an h3 of
each of the task
text okay so um
in addition to that we have a warning
that says
each child in a list should have a
unique key prop
so when we use dot map in here and we
output jsx that's called a list
so the parent of the list which in this
case is an h3
should have a key prop and that should
be something unique so we'll use the
task.id
because those are unique so if i save
that and we reload that's going to get
rid of the console warning down here
now ultimately like i said that we don't
want this to be separate from our
component
we want this to be part of our state so
what i'm going to do is
just cut the array itself
and delete this and to use state inside
of a function
we use whoops we use a hook called use
state
so let's say imports and then in curly
braces
we want to take you state and that's
from react directly
okay now the way we do this is above the
return we're going to say const
brackets and then what we want to call
this piece of state which is tasks
and then a function to to update the
state which we're going to call
set tasks we want to set that to use
state and then in here is the default
that we want to use for this piece of
state for our tasks which i'm going to
go ahead and just paste in
that array all right now if i save this
you'll see that there's no difference
here because
this tasks variable is still you know
it's still being used right here
except instead of having it come from
outside of our component
it's now part of our component state if
we wanted to change
any part of the state we would use set
tasks it's important to know that you
wouldn't do
something like tasks dot push if you
wanted to add to it because state is
immutable it's not something that you
can directly change
you basically recreate it and send it
down it's it's it's one-way data
so you would to do that you would use
set tasks instead
and then change it to you know whatever
you want if you wanted to spread across
what's already there and then add a new
um
a new object you could do that now
we don't really want to have our tasks
in
the tasks component because
we're going to want to access these from
other components
so you could use something like the
context api or redux
where you would have a kind of a store
that that hovers over your
ui where you could pull you know
different
pieces of state from but we're not going
to get into that so
what we want to do is just put it in our
app.js that will make it our global
state then we can pass it down into
components that we want as props
so what i'll do is take this
we'll cut that out and we're going to
instead put that in our app.js
and then i'm also going to take this
whole thing where we define this
task and set tasks and
cut that
all right and then we're going to put
that in our app
so this is going to break for a second
don't worry about that but we're going
to put that in here
so now this is part of our app component
state or our app level state
and what we can do is take our task and
pass them in to our task component
as a prop so we want to set tasks
equals tasks it's still not going to
work because
tasks right here isn't defined
but remember it's being passed in as a
prop we could do props and then props
dot tasks
or we can just do structure and
tasks and now it works okay if i reload
console should clear
so now we have our state where it should
be which is at the top
level because we want to be able to use
these within other components
or we may want to if we keep it in task
we can't we can only use it
in you know components we embed
in here or we would have to send it up
it's just it gets really messy so
the next thing i want to do is instead
of just rendering out
an h3 for each task i want to have a
separate task
component so let's create a new file
called just task
singular js and let's create a component
and what we'll do here um how do i want
to
style this or format this let's do
a div and give this a class name
uh oh you know what my css i believe is
wrong i have events because i was going
to use events instead of tasks let me
just change this this will be different
this will be correct in your version but
let's say task
instead of event
and save that okay so now we'll set this
class name
equal to task and then in here we'll
have an
h
and we're going to get passed in here
actually for now let's just say
my task and then what i'll do is in
our tasks we'll import
the singular task component so that's
going to be from
dot slash task and then instead of an
h3 this is actually going to be a task
component
and instead of doing this like instead
of wrapping this i'm just going to
get rid of that go like that we're still
going to have the id but we want to pass
in each task as a prop
okay so we're looping through them here
and then we're outputting a component
and we're passing the task in as a prop
so we'll save that and now all we're
seeing is my task because that's all
we're putting here
however we're going to catch that prop
we're going to take in the
actually we don't yeah we'll just say
task
and in the h3
we'll say task dot i think it's text
yep so now we're seeing our task text
task text
i feel like i'm saying a freaking
nursery rhyme song
so in addition to that we're going to
want let's do a paragraph and we have
the day so task dot day
save that there we go looks good um
see what else do we want to do we're
going to want to have an a delete icon
so i guess we can do that um you could
include the
i'm going to use font awesome you could
include font awesome the cdn
in your index html in your public folder
however what i'm going to do is install
react icons which allows you to use
multiple icon libraries
so i'm going to leave my dev server
running open a new tab
and say npm install react dash
icons
so that way we can just bring in an icon
that we want to use
and use it instead of you know using a
cdn
okay so react icons is installed and if
you look in your package.json
you should see react icons anything you
install with npm
as long as it's not as long as it's
local and not global you're going to see
in here
so we want to bring in a specific icon
so we're basically using icons as react
components we're going to bring in
fa times which is the x icon
from react icons and then slash
fa for font awesome because there's
multiple libraries that you can use with
this
and then i'm going to go let's see let's
go within the
h3 right here so after the after the
text
we're going to put in f a times just
like we would put in
any component and save
and i think we have to restart the
server after we install react icons
so i'm going to go back to my dev server
and stop that control c
command c npm start
and there we go so now you can see we
have the x icons
i am just going to i want to make them
red so i'm going to add a style
to this so say
we want the color to be red
and let's make the cursor
a pointer
all right so now we have our delete
icons now we want to make it so that
when we click this
it deletes that particular event but
how do we do that when we don't have
access to the events here remember the
the events are stored in the
app.js and the app component now if you
were using like the context api or redux
there's ways to to access your state
from within components
pretty easily but redux i mean there's a
lot of boilerplate and it can be a
little difficult to learn like reducers
and stuff like that
so in this case what we can do is just
use props we can send
down a function as a prop and then
fire that off when we click in here so
in the app.js
let's create a function so whenever we
want to delete a task or add or anything
like that it's going to be in this file
so let's say delete task and we'll
create
a function called delete task
and that's going to take in a specific
id
and for now we're just going to console
log the text delete and we'll
also log the id all right now
we're going to pass in a prop to
tasks because remember a task where the
where the actual button is
that is in the task.js and then that's
in tasks
so we want to pass in let's call this
prop on delete
and basically when that's fired off it's
going to call delete
event all right now on delete is now a
prop
of oops delete event i'm sorry delete
task i'm going to do that a few times
through this
because i decided to change it to tasks
at the last minute
so this is going to be delete task
all right and then on delete is going to
be
a prop of tasks so just like we passed
in tasks we want to pass
in on delete and then that's going to
get passed in here as a prop as well
because that's where we want to
use it so on delete equals
on delete and then in task
again pass in on delete as a prop
however we want to call that
on a click right so in this fa times
let's say on click and set that to
on delete which is going to
basically work its way up to here
and call delete task so state gets
passed down
actions get passed up so if i click this
we do get the delete text but we also
see this event stuff
because that's what's being passed in
here by default
if i want to actually pass the id in
what i have to do is in
on the on click here instead of calling
onto undelete directly
we call a function and then call on
delete and pass in
the task.id so now
if i click on one of these i get delete
one delete two delete three
so we're able to now click on these and
call this function
which is in the app.js where we have
access to the state
all right now in order to actually
delete
get rid of that console log so we want
to call set
tasks because that's how we deal with
with this with our mutable state and
we're going to take the tasks that are
already there and just
filter so dot filter is a high order
array method
you should really know this stuff before
getting into react but
basically this takes in a function so
we'll say for each
task i want to filter so we're going to
filter where let's say
task dot id if the task id is not
equal to the id though that's what i
want to show i don't want to show
the task with the id because we're
deleting it
okay so this is just within the ui
so if we save that and i reload and i
click on the x here you'll see that it
goes away
because it's filtering out it's setting
the tasks to the filtered tasks
all right now if i wanted to make it so
it shows like a message if there's no
tasks
i could go down to here
and wrap this in
curly braces and i could say
if tasks dot length
if it's greater than zero then
show tasks else show nothing
so if i save that wait what am i doing
if task.length else show nothing no i
want to show
no tasks to
show all right so there we go so if
there's nothing there it's just going to
give us that message
if i reload they're all going to come
back because remember this is just the
ui that's what react does
you can turn this into a full stack
application by having a back end
some kind of api that you can make
requests to and
fetch data from which we might do at the
end with something called json server
all right so we're able to delete these
now
let's do the um
let's do the reminder i want to be able
to double click
and add a specific class and if you look
in the css
i have a class called reminder with a
green border on the left so basically
what we want to happen is when we double
click we want to change
whatever task we're double clicking
change the reminder to the opposite of
whatever it's set
and if it's true have that border so
i'm gonna again start in the app.js just
like we just did with the delete
and let's say toggle reminder
and we'll create a function here let's
call it
toggle reminder
and it's going to need the id because it
needs to know which one to toggle
all right actually let's call it
reminder no that's that's fine
so toggle reminder
and for now again i'm just going to
console.log
the id and we need to pass this down
just like we did with the delete so
inside task
let's say on we'll say on toggle
and set that to toggle
reminder and then in tasks
also pass in the prop of on toggle
or i should say catch the prop and then
here
pass into a prop of on toggle set that
to
on toggle and then inside task what we
want to do is on the div
okay not on the um not on the
on the delete button obviously we want
to do this on the main div
so i'm going to add let's say on
double click and we're going to set that
to and this should get passed in on
toggle
so on double click we're going to call
on
toggle all right now again we need the
id
so let's just do a function and then
call on toggle and pass
in the id so now
id is not defined that's because it
should be task
dot id because we're passing in the task
as a prop
all right so now if i double click one
of these it's going to show the id
so when i double click it runs this
right here
now what do we want this to do we want
this to
of course toggle the reminder either
from true to false or
from false to true so there's
a bunch of ways you can do this i'm
going to use of course we need to use
set tasks and
i'm going to use map so we're going to
say tasks which is our state
our task in our state we want to map
through
and for each one we'll call it task
and i'm going to say where the task
dot id so if the task id
that were you know in the current
iteration is
equal to the id that's passed in
then we're going to have a specific
object
else it's just going to be the the task
is no change right because we don't we
only want to change the one that we're
dealing with
so for the one that we're dealing with
the object i want to copy or
i should say spread across all of the
task properties and values
but i want to change the reminder so the
reminder i'm going to set to the
opposite of whatever that specific
task reminder is if it's false it'll be
true if it's true it'll be false
so i'm going to go ahead and save that
and i haven't even used the react dev
tools yet so if we go down to components
here
we can see our component tree
we have each task and if you hover on
that you can see the different props the
task itself
on toggle on delete what i want to look
at is
we could look at this but let's look at
app
and you can see our state right here
which is our three
tasks and if i look at the first one
doctor's appointment
reminder is set to true now if i double
click
now it's set to false okay because we
double clicked it called this function
and we set that particular
task to change the reminder to the
opposite of what it was
if i click it again goes to true so we
know that's working
but there's no there's no there's
nothing in the ui that lets us know that
so what we'll do is go back into task
and remember we have that specific class
of
reminder that we'll add a border to to
the edge
so let's go so we have class name equals
task
what i'm going to do here is make this
into an expression
and some backticks and i still want the
task
class that's going to be there no matter
what and then i want
a condition here so in a
template literal here we're going to say
if the
task dot reminder
is true then
we're going to have the class of
reminder
else then it's just going to be nothing
so if i save that you can see the first
two
have the green border because those are
true if i double click
it goes away double click again comes
back
okay so it's this is coming down from
our state
this task and we're checking the
reminder
okay so we can just toggle these and we
can delete them
now it goes back to the default because
we're just setting i mean this is just
kind of like static data
that we have as our default data
if you're using a back end you'd be
making fetch requests or http requests
to your server
as well so now let's start to work
on the the ad form because we haven't
even created that yet so in components
i'm going to create
add let's call this add task
dot js and we'll go ahead and create a
component
now this is going to be a form so
instead of a div this will be a form
we'll give this a
class name of add
dash form and then each
each label and input is going to be
wrapped in a class of form control so
let's say
div class name and set that to
form control and then we'll have
a label so this label
will just say
we'll just say task for the label and
then input
will have a type of text
and let's add a placeholder and set that
to
add task
okay there's other stuff we're going to
add to this but i just want to get the
form
displayed for now so i'm going to copy
this form control down
twice and this next one is going to be
the
day we'll say day and time
type is text and then for this we'll
just say add
day and time then this one is going to
be
let's say reminder or set reminder
and it's going to be a check box so
let's change change the type to
check box and get rid of the placeholder
we don't need that
and then i just want to have a submit so
we'll do an input
with the type of submit and then let's
have a value
the value will be save or
save task all right so we'll save that
and then let's just
we'll embed this into our app.js so i'm
going to copy this down and
set that to add task set that to
add task and then
right below let's see right below the
header
add task now if i save that we should
see our form
uh oh one thing i forgot is some classes
just the styling so this the check box
form control
i also have form control
i think it's just form control check
yeah and then for the button down here
the input submit
let's say class name and that's going to
be set to um
btn and btn
block okay let's make that look a little
better
and let's just open up our console make
sure we have no errors
all right now each input is going to
have its own piece of state
component level state not app level
state so
let's bring in
use state
from not const what am i doing
report use state from
[Music]
react and then right above the return
we're going to have
first one is text and set text is the
method to
update the state the default is just an
empty string
and then we have set day
for the day input
and then we have reminder
set reminder and the default for
reminder is going to be false
all right so we have that now down in
the input the first one of text let's go
right here and the value of this is
going to be
the text from the state but we also need
an on change because when you start to
type in the input that's going to fire
off this on change it's a controlled
component
so this is going to have a function
we're going to pass in the event
object and directly call set text from
here
and set it to e dot target dot
value which is going to be whatever is
typed in all right
so i'm going to copy this value and on
change
and go to the next one of day except
this is going to be day instead of text
and the function to change that is going
to be set
day and again it will be set to the
target value which is whatever is typed
in
so check box i'll paste that in this is
going to be
the reminder state and this will be set
reminder
right and then instead of target.value
because this isn't an input it's a
checkbox
we can get current
target dot checked which will give us
either a true or false value
if that's checked or not all right so
that should clear up if i
reload now to check this
if we go to our react dev tools so down
here where it says components
we can see all of our components and if
we go to add tasks
we should be able to see our state
so right here you can see each one of
these is the three inputs
if i start to type in the text
and i say text because that's what we
called
you know that piece of state we can see
it down here if i type in
a day we can see that if i check set
reminder
you can see that that all right so we
know that's working
now as far as submitting this
we're going to have to have a function
in our app.js because we're going to be
dealing with our tasks
so let's put this above the delete we'll
say add
task and let's say const
add task
so for now let's just do a console log
it's going to take
in as far as what this takes
in we'll just
say task
and yeah we'll just console log that
now we have to pass this in or we have
to pass a prop into
add task let's say on add and
then that's going to call add task
okay now in our add task component we
want to take in
on add and
what i'm going to do is add a submit
event here so
on submit and set that to
on submit and then on submit is going to
be defined
in here const on submit because there's
a few things we need to do
so we're not calling on add directly
so on submit that's going to take in the
event object because we need to e dot
prevent default so it doesn't actually
submit to a page
and then once we do that i just want to
do a little bit of validation for the
the text the task
text so let's do let's say if
and we'll say if not text
then oops and we're talking about this
piece of state which is connected to
this input so if that's not there then
let's do an alert
and say please add a task
and then return all right if that
passes then we're going to call on add
and we want to pass in
into on add we want to pass in an object
with
the text the day
and the reminder okay then i also want
to clear the form so i'm going to
call set text again and clear it
and then we want to clear day
set day and then set reminder
which is a boolean so that's going to
get set to false
all right now i want i want it to be
unchecked if it's false
so down here we have our check
check boxes can take to take in a
checked value which will be true or
false so i'm going to say
if reminder so if that's true then
actually no we can just set it to yeah
set it to reminder
yeah so we'll save that
okay now when i submit this what should
happen is it should
cause it should check to see if text is
there so if i don't have that
filled in i'll get an alert then it
should call on add
which is just going to call
add task which up here is going to
console log the task so let's open up
our console
and we're just going to type whatever in
here
and save so the form also cleared
and down here you can see that we have
our data
now instead of console logging we we
want to add this to our state
so in order to do that i mean there's
there's a bunch of ways we could do that
i do want to add an id since we're not
dealing with a data a backend
where it creates an id on on its own i'm
just going to do something really simple
here and use math dot
floor which will round down math
uh we'll say math dot
random we'll make it uh up to like ten
thousand
and plus one so that should just give me
a random number so if we console log id
and i just submit this it should just
log a random number good
so we have an id so now i'm going to
just create
let's say new task and this new task is
going to be an object with that id
and then i'm going to copy whatever the
task
text day and reminder which is passed in
here
i'm going to add that to the object as
well
all right then we want to use set
tasks and we're going to set it
as an array we're going to copy the
current
tasks that are already there but then we
also want to add the new
task onto it all right so let's save
that
and now we should be able to add a new
task i'll just say test
one test two set reminder
save task and there it is and we can
change the reminder we can delete it so
now we're able to add it
cool so the next thing i want to do is
this button here
should toggle this form we want it to
start off not
showing but then we want to click this
show it click it again
to toggle it so we're going to have
another piece of state in our app.js
and we're going to call that let's say
const
let's say what do we want to call this
we'll say show add
task and then set show add
task which is going to be a boolean so
set this to use state
set it to false by default and then this
form is going to be dependent on that
piece of state so down where we're
embedding add
tasks let's wrap this in curly braces
and say if show add task is true
then show that component
now this is just a shorter way of doing
a ternary without an
else okay we don't need an else we just
want to see if it's true if it is do
this if not nothing
so we'll save that and now it's not
showing now if i set the default of that
show add task to true
then it's going to show it by default
all right now
we want this button to toggle that so
we're going to have to do a couple
things with that
now that button is inside of the header
so if we go down to header
let's say let's have a prop called on
add
now when that's fired off we'll have a
function
and we'll call set show
add task we want to set it to the
opposite of whatever the value is so the
opposite of
show add task now on
add is going to get passed into header
as a prop
so let's say on add
and right now the button on click is
just set to this
right here on click we just want to get
rid of that
and change on click to on add
so if we save that and just open up our
console here as well
so if we save that i click add it shows
the form
i click it again it goes away
okay now i think we should also change
the button if it's open
change the text to close we could even
change the color
so to do that let's see we'll go back to
app.js
and where we have our header
in addition to the on add prop let's
also just pass in
whatever the value of show
show ad task is so we'll set
show add task to whatever
show add task
actually we can just call this prop show
add
all right and then back in the header
say show add and it's just going to be
either
true or false if it's being shown or not
so if it
is let's see so the text right now just
says add let's change that to be dynamic
and we'll say if show
add so if that's true that means we want
to show
that means we want to show close right
because it's
being shown else then we'll show add
so save that and now it says close if i
click it
now it says add now also change the
color it's set to green right now so
we'll change that
let's say if show add then
let's make it red else
then we'll make it green
so now it's red close it now it's green
so you can see how
this is where how this is where react is
really valuable it allows you to make
really dynamic
interfaces and no pages are being
reloaded or anything like that
so i mean this is a really small
application but you can see the value in
this
and i mean it might be a little
intimidating at first
but you can you really get the hang of
it and you you see how valuable it is
to do stuff like this in vanilla
javascript is it's just very messy and
unorganized and much more difficult
so let's see what's next we can show our
ad form we can add we can delete we can
set
toggle i think that we're pretty much
done as far as like
just the ui goes i would like to get
into
some http stuff dealing with a back end
there's something called json server
that we can use it's kind of a mock back
end
um so i think that will do that but
before we get into any of that
like making requests i just want to show
you how you would actually build your
static assets out
if you're ready to deploy so
and it says right here use yarn build or
npm run build depends on you know if you
use yarn or npm
but if i go ahead and i'm going to stop
the server for a second and you'll see
that this
by reload doesn't work and i'm going to
run npm
run build and it's going to create a
an optimized production build in a
folder called build
and this is going to be your static
assets this is what you would deploy
and this used to confuse me when i first
got into react was or any framework like
this
do i deploy my components folder or does
the browser see that
like i mean it was kind of confusing but
no that's all your development stuff
build is where your is is your build
folder that's your
where you push to production now if you
want to try this locally
you could install the npm serve
serve package globally so we can go
ahead and do that so let's say
npm install dash g actually after you if
you're on a mac or linux you'll have to
use sudo for
permissions because we're installing
this globally
and then serve
it's just this is just a basic http
server
so i should now be able to
[Music]
serve let's say serv
dash s and then the build folder
and then i want to serve it on a port
let's say
dash p 8000
all right so now if i go to and remember
locals 3000 isn't working that's our dev
server if i go to 8 000
there it is all right so
this now if you look at the react dev
tools
icon it's blue not orange and it says
this page is using the production build
so this is your production build this is
what you would deploy i could delete all
the rest of these folders right now and
this would still work
because this is our production build all
right i hope that makes sense so i'm
going to stop this
and if you want to stop here that's fine
i'm going to keep going
so that you can see how to deal with
kind of a mock
back end now there's a
there's a really cool tool called
json server and it basically allows us
to create a mock rest api with our own
data
so we install it we're not going to
install it globally you will install it
locally
and then you can create a db.json with
some resources and you can make
post requests put requests patch and all
that just like as if it were a real back
end
built with you know node.js and express
or django
or laravel or whatever it might be so
before we start our react server backup
let's say
npm install json server
and this will install it locally so it's
going to get put in our package.json
if you clone this repository it'll be
included in here
now we need a way to run this so i'm
actually going to create another script
here
called server and this is going to run
json dash server and dash
dash watch and then the port
i'm going to run this on 5000 because i
believe
the default port is 3000
and we also have to put the name of the
file db.json
all right so this will run our server we
can pretend that this is like a real
backend that we created a rest api
so let's run here npm
run server
and you can see it actually created a
db.json
with some posts we're going to delete
this stuff but we also want to run our
dev server as well so i'm going to open
up a new tab
and run npm start that's our react dev
server
and the idea is we want to get data from
here
into here so first of all let's change
this data up so this is going to be
tasks
and we'll delete get rid of that
we just want our brackets and then i
guess what we can do is just copy
excuse me copy the from app.js
these objects oops
these task objects we'll cut those
out and this is the use state right here
for tasks is going to be just an empty
array if i save that
we're going to see no tasks to show and
that's that's fine
so here i'll paste those objects in
however we need to
change these to uh json objects
which means that the keys have to have
double quotes and any strings have to
have
double quotes so just
add these
and no trailing commas either
get rid of that now
jason server actually creates ids for
you just like a real database just like
a real back end would
so we're not going to even have to worry
about creating ids
all right so that looks good
now let's see
close that up so the first thing we'll
do is
fill is let's fetch our tasks from the
back end from what
and you can even do this right from your
browser http localhost
5000 slash
tasks and there we go we can also make
post put and delete requests
so in order to load them when the page
loads we're going to use a hook
called use effect which is used to
create side effects or deal with side
effects
and it's often used to if you want
something to happen right when the page
loads
so we'll use this right below where we
did our use states
say use effect and this takes in an
arrow function
and we're going to be using the fetch
api with a sync away now we can't
do a sync like this on this function so
we have to create one
in here let's call it let's say fetch
tasks
and set that to a sync
and then here let's say kant's response
or res
equals await because fetch returns a
promise so we want to await that promise
and http localhost
port 5000 slash tasks
okay then we want the data so const data
equals
we want to await res.json that will give
us the json data
we'll console log the data and then of
course we have to call
fetch tasks all right so we'll save that
we also want to add a dependency array
here
if you have a value where you want this
to run if that value changes you would
pass it in here
like user or something we don't have any
dependencies but you want to pass
in just an empty array
alright so now you can see as soon as
the page loads we're getting this data
we're getting it from our json server
which
you could replace with any back end
so in instead of
just console logging we obviously we
want to set this
data as our state however i don't want
to have fetch
tasks in use effect because i might want
to use this somewhere else
so i'm not going to call set tasks right
here what i'm going to do is return
the data and then i'm going to take this
out
and cut that out and just put it right
below a views effect
fetch data from actually let's just say
fetch tasks okay and then
what we'll do is instead have a function
called get tasks
and it's going to be async because we're
going to call fetchtask which returns a
promise
so here let's say
we'll do cons we'll call this
tasks from server
and then we want to await fetch
tasks and then from there we'll call set
tasks which will add it to our state and
we want to add
tasks from server
and then instead of calling fetchtask
here we're going to call
gettasks all right so if i save that
what's this each list should have a
unique
key prop
uh this should have a unique key prop
should have the id
let me uh let me console console.log
what we're getting here
yes we have the id and then in our
component
tasks
key id i'm not sure why
i'm not sure what i'm missing here
i guess we could use the index if
let's say index
all right so that gets rid of that
so we're able to fetch our tasks from
the back end
and display them so the next thing i
want to do
is be able to delete them so we already
have a delete and it's going to delete
from the ui
just fine but if i reload they're back
because
they're we haven't deleted them from the
server
so let's go down to where we have our
delete
so we have delete task and this is going
to be
pretty simple because we just need to
make a simple delete request
right before we you know filter through
the ui
so let's go ahead and make this an async
function and we're going to just await
we don't need to save it in a variable
because we're not
getting any data back but we're going to
call
fetch and here we're going to use
backticks
http localhost
5000 slash tasks
slash and then the id
now we want to add a second argument of
an object where we specify
the method of this request to be a
delete
all right so we'll go ahead and delete
that
and it will filter from the ui
so let's save that and let's try let's
delete food shopping
so it deletes from the ui if i reload
it's gone okay
and we should see if we look in the
where our json server is running you can
see all of the different requests that
are made and all of the responses
so we'll just keep that open as well
so next thing let's see we're able to
we're able to list them delete them
let's do the
no we'll do the add okay so we want to
be able to add a task
and have it persist to our back end
so let's see we have our add task right
here
now again we're not going to need to
create an id
because it assigns an id for us
so we can actually just you know what
i'll do is i'll comment this out just in
case you guys need it
and i'll go above it okay so we're gonna
want to
response and we want this to be a sync
and then a weight fetch
and we're adding a task so the route is
going to be http
localhost
5000 slash tasks and it's going to be a
post request so we want to add
here a method of post
since we're adding data we need to add
headers
because we need to specify our content
type
and that's going to be application
slash jason and then we also want to set
outside of headers we want to set the
body that we're sending the data we're
sending
which we're going to wrap in
json.stringify which is just going to
turn it from
you know a javascript object into a json
string
and what we're sending is the task
and that's getting passed in here all
right so that's the
request response then we want to
let's get the data here say res.json
now the data that's returned is just the
new task that's added
so then once that once we do that we
want to call set
tasks again we want to set it remember
tasks is the entire array
we're going to take the existing tasks
and then we're going to add on to it
data which is the new task that was just
created
so let's save that and let's go over
here and we'll say um
i don't know we'll say take test
monday and set reminder so we'll save
task all right so that
didn't seem to work okay so it did work
on the server side
but this part didn't work
um
oh we didn't await so this this is a
promise we have to make sure we await
res.json
all right so let's delete take tests
that should that should persist
and then we'll say take test
i'll say friday this time and
there we go so now it gets added to the
ui or added to the server and then added
to the ui
okay so that's all set now one thing i
note i i noticed
was in my db.json the second one here
just had a d and not an id and i think
that was the reason
why i was getting that key error earlier
so just make sure that each one has an
id
all right now the last thing we want to
do here
in terms of working with the server is
updating the uh
the reminder so if i double click that
it works in the ui but
it doesn't we haven't made a request to
the server
so that's going to happen in toggle
reminder but
first i want to be able to get a single
task
from the server so i'm going to go up
here where i have fetch
tasks and just copy that it's going to
be very very similar
just called fetch task singular and it's
going to take
in an id and we want to change these to
backticks
and do slash
id okay so we have fetch task
and then we're going to go down to
toggle reminder
and it's basically just an update we're
not able to update like the name you can
add that on if you want we're just
updating a single field but it's done
the same way really
so let's let's first
go ahead and create we'll say task
to toggle so which one do we want to
grab
so that's going to come from let's say a
weight
fetch task singular and pass in the id
now this has to be a sync
so we're going to get the task to toggle
then we're going to put it into a
variable the updated
task which is going to be an event
it's going to have all the same
properties of tasks to toggle so we're
just spreading those across here
in addition to that we want to change
reminder
to whatever the opposite of task
to toggle dot reminder is
we want reminder
okay so we haven't made any requests or
anything we're just
getting the task and then creating the
new task and putting it in a variable
now let's say const res equals
await fetch and
let's see we're doing an update so we're
going to want the id so http
localhost port 5000 slash
task slash id
then we want to add a method of put
since this is an update we want to add
headers since we're sending data
we want the content type
of the data we're sending application
slash
json and whoops not here but under
headers
we want the body which is the data we're
sending wrapped in json.stringify to
turn it into a string
and it's going to be the task
i'm sorry the updated task
all right then we want to just
data awaits
on the response jason
and then the only thing we want to
change right here is the reminder we're
setting it to whatever the data
reminded because the data that we get
back is just the updated task
so whatever that is true or false we're
going to have here
if it matches that id so let's save that
and let's open that up
so i'm going to double click meeting at
school you can see down here put request
to task
2 200 response so if i reload it stays
off or it stays false if i make them all
true
and reload that stays all right so we're
now
able to interact with our server in all
ways we can delete we can add
we're fetching our data so this is what
you would do in a full stack app except
instead of using json server you would
build your own rest api
with whatever language and framework you
choose
all right now one thing we haven't
gotten into is routing and that's the
last thing i want to cover
so we've done everything just within
this single this one page right here
this one
view really so to
use routing there's no routing included
with the core library
i'm just gonna let's see i'll just open
a new tab here
so we use a package called react router
dom so let's
npm install react dash
router dash dom
and that's going to show up in our
package.json
okay so there it is now
in our app.js
if we look at you know what we're
returning let's go back down here look
at what we're returning
we have a container with our header our
add
task which is dependent on this value
our tasks component you know which will
show if there's
if there actually is any tasks and then
that's pretty much it so i want to first
of all add a footer
and i want to have in that footer a link
to an about page that has an about
component
so in components let's create a new
file called footer.js
and we'll go ahead and create a
component here
uh we'll get rid of this
so this footer is going to be pretty
simple i'm just going to change this to
footer
and then let's let's put a
paragraph and we'll just say copyright
ampersand copy semicolon 2021 and then
under that i'm going to have a link
to this is going to go to slash about
i'm going to change this after but just
have that for now
and then we're going to bring this into
our app.js up at the top
so import actually i'll just
copy header down and
change that to footer
and we're just gonna embed this down
here in our return
all right so there's our footer now for
routes let's say let's create our
about first about component so about.js
so this is going to be really simple i'm
just going to put
an h4 and say this say the version
1.0.0 and then we'll put uh
let's put a link to go back
that'll go to slash go back
all right now this about
component i'm going to bring into app.js
and of course i could just embed it like
we've been doing but i want to use the
router
so we need to bring in
let's say import from
react router dom and what we want to
bring in
are two things we want to bring in
browser router
which will use the html5 push state i'm
going to
give it an alias of router though and
then we also want to bring in route
so to use the router we have to wrap
everything in our output
so in our return right here we're going
to wrap everything in
router all right so i'm going to grab
that
and put that down here
so now since we wrap that in router we
can use routes
so right above the footer i'm going to
say
route and pass in a path
of slash about and then pass in
a component and that component is going
to be
about now if i save that if i click on
about
i can see the about component i can see
the other ones as well
because they're just embedded up here so
any route we create we're always going
to see those which i want to change
now it's not going to be as easy as just
labeling a component because we
i want to put the add task component and
the tasks
component all in one route all in the
index route
so to do that we can say route
and path set to slash
we also want to add exact or else if we
go the about it's going to do the same
thing and show this
just because it's going to first match
the slash so we want to
match this exactly and then instead of
component we can use
render and inside render it just takes
an
arrow function with props
and we'll point this function to a set
of parentheses and in here we're just
going to have
a fragment and then we can take whatever
we want which is going to be the add
task and the tasks
so we'll cut those and we're going to
put that put that right in here in this
route render
now if i save that you can see we're on
slash about
right and we don't see the other stuff
if we go back
now we see the add and the
the tasks all right
so let's see next thing
notice when i click on about or go back
see how the reload and up here see how
the page reloads we don't want that
so to stop that from happening instead
of using an a tag
for instance let's go to the about page
instead of using an a tag we're
going to use link from react router dom
so let's say import
link from
uh react router dom and then we just
replace
an eight the a tag with link
and replace href with two
all right we're gonna do the same thing
where else do we have this in the footer
where we're linking to the about page
we're going to do the same thing
and change that to link and change that
to 2.
and now you'll notice if i click about
or go back
it doesn't reload it's just instant so
you want to make sure if you're using
routes that you use
link as opposed to just regular link a
tags
all right and you can obviously create
as many components as you want and
as many routes you can also put multiple
components with props like we did here
the last thing if we go to about we
still see this ad which doesn't make
sense
so to get rid of that we could go to our
header
so in our header there's something
called use location it's actually a hook
that we can use from react router dom
so i'm gonna
import use location
from oops
from react router dom
and this allows us to basically look at
the route that we're currently on
so above the return here let's just
create a variable
called location and we'll set that to
use
location and then we should have access
to location.path name so where we have
this button let's wrap it in
curly braces so we can add a condition
and we'll say if location
dot path name is equal to
slash then
we'll go ahead and show the button all
right so save that
and now notice on the about page the
button's gone if i go back to the index
there it is
all right so you can you can check out
the whatever the path name is or the
route is
and you can do certain things based on
that route
all right so that's routing uh and i
think that's it guys i mean we covered a
lot this was a long video
longer than i expected and i actually
wanted to do routing before we did all
the http
stuff with jason server so i apologize
for that
i kind of forgot about it so uh that's
it hopefully this taught you
uh something even if you didn't catch
everything if this is your first time
dealing with react and this just
looks like a horror show to you don't
worry about it
you're gonna get more familiar with it
as you learn it as you watch more videos
i have an entire playlist of different
projects i have three udemy courses
uh if you're interested uh myrn stat
courses
and so on and there's just tons of
content out there the documentation
look at other people's code you know to
get examples
um uh to kind of learn what's going on
so there's there's a lot of things you
can do so don't get overwhelmed if this
looks really hard
but um that's it thanks for watching
guys i really appreciate it if you
lasted this long
and i will see you next time